# Abhishek Prannath Tiwari

Mumbai, India abhishektiwariaman@gmail.com | +91 9579202967 https://www.linkedin.com/in/the-abhishek-tiwari/

https://github.com/abhishekptiwari

I work as a Backend Software Engineer at IN10 Media Network. With 5 years of experience in Node.js, I have honed my skills in various advanced technologies, including React.js, Express.js, MongoDB, AWS, MySQL, Linux, Redis, and Memcached. I have strong expertise in Node.js, APIs, and system design.

### **EDUCATION**

**Kishinchand Chellaram College**, Bachelor of Information Technology (**B.sc-IT**)

2019 - 2022 Mumbai, India

#### TECHNICAL SKILL SET

Front End Languages: HTML, CSS, JavaScript,

ReactJS & Redux, AJAX.

Back End Languages: Node.js, Express.js, Java, C++

Databases: MongoDB, MySQL, Redis,

Cloud Technology: AWS

**Build Tools:** Docker & Docker Swarm

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

**Software Engineer-II** Oct 2023 - Present

IN10 Media Network Pvt. Ltd, India

- Working on DocuBay OTT D2C and Telcos (Telecommunication Portal) systems.
- Decreased the load time of the initial home page by 3x for a better user experience.
- Built a content recommendation engine from scratch using Numpy, Pandas, NLTK, and Scikit-learn in Python.
- Decoupled the complex application logic into a microservices-based architecture to maintain high availability.
- Managed multiple applications using Docker Swarm and deployed them on cloud services (AWS).
- Managed, created, tested, and integrated APIs on both the frontend and backend, deploying stable versions of the project to UAT and production servers.

# **MERN Stack Developer**

Apr 2023 - Oct 2023

Kuruvila Technologies Pvt. Ltd, India

- Created, tested, and managed all backend internal and external APIs.
- Integrated payment gateways: BillDesk, Razorpay, and PayU to accept payments.
- Optimized database queries and operations, reducing API response times.
- Integrated n8n automation tool to automate scheduled & event-driven tasks, and deployed it on the live server.
- Optimized the backend source code written in Node. is using batch processing and optimized MySQL queries.
- Managed and assigned tasks to individual team members, deployed a stable version of the project to the UAT & Production Server, monitored processes, and resolved issues.

# **Software Engineer-I**

Feb 2022 - Apr 2023

Qtech Software Pvt. Ltd. India

- Responsible for B2B, B2C, Upsale, and notification application development, integration, testing, and maintenance of APIs
- Establishing user authentication and authorization across many settings, servers, and systems.
- Responsible for developing, implementing, and testing Rest APIs between multiple applications.
- Designing an application architecture from scratch and putting concepts into practice in real-world situations.
- Overcoming development obstacles and choosing an architectural style by grasping the project's overall objectives.

Software Developer Oct 2021 - Feb 2022

Swift Robotics, London, England, United Kingdom

- Learning ROS to Integrate with Application.
- Website Development/Mobile Application Development. (React.js)

# **Backend Web Developer**

Jul 2021 - Nov 2021

21 Event and Tech. Pvt. Ltd, India

- Data Migration. (In Adonis.js alternative framework of express.js).
- Code migration from adonis.js 4.1 to 5.0

### **Web Application Developer**

May 2020 - Jul 2021

freelancer.com, India

- Build a fast, scalable, feature-rich RESTful API (includes filters, sorts, pagination, and much more).
- How to work with data in NoSQL databases (including geospatial data).
- Security: encryption, sanitization, rate limiting, etc.
- Deploy the final application to production (including a Git).
- Server-side website rendering with EJS templates.
- Advanced authentication and authorization (including password reset).
- Deep dive into Mongoose (including all advanced features).

#### **PROJECTS**

DocuBay.com Oct 2023 – Present

- DocuBay is a global membership video-on-demand platform designed specifically for streaming documentaries from around the world.
- DocuBay is available across all devices and is accessible in more than 150 countries.
- Roles and responsibilities: Working as a Backend Software Engineer, responsible for creating, testing, and deploying APIs and applications on different cloud servers. Managing tasks and JIRA sprints, coordinating with teams and managers, and resolving issues as they arise.
- Technologies Used: Javascript, Reactjs, Nodejs, Expressjs, Redis, MongoDB, ElasticSearch, Docker & AWS.

#### **Content Recommendation Engine**

Dec 2023 - May 2024

- Data cleaning & Preprocessing: Cleaned and integrated data using Pandas and Numpy library for seamless recommendation processing.
- **Text Vectorization:** Employed NLTK and Scikit-learn to convert text into vectors for accurate content recommendations.
- Model Training: Developed and trained a recommendation model, stored as a pickle file for efficient use.
- **Real-time Recommendations:** Built a Flask application with APIs to deliver real-time content recommendations.
- **End-to-end Automation:** Automated the entire recommendation process, ensuring scalability and real-time undates.
- Technologies Used: Python3, Pandas, Numpy, NLTK, scikit-learn, Streamlit, Flask, MongoDB, Redis.

rePUSHTI.com Feb 2022 - Apr 2023

- rePUSHTI is a cloud platform that completely automates your booking re-verification process. It provides a hassle-free, accurate, and detailed re-verification of your bookings through our AI-powered engine.
- It offers complete control through a real-time dashboard, reducing errors and overbookings for a seamless experience.
- Roles and responsibilities: Worked as a Backend Web Developer. Contributed to third-party API integration (WhatsApp, Gmail, Microsoft Outlook, etc.). Created an API Gateway and a separate notification node application to deliver notifications through different mediums: SMS, WhatsApp, and Email.
- Technologies Used: Javascript, Nodejs, Expressjs, EJS, HTML, CSS, JQuery, AWS.

# **CERTIFICATIONS AND RECOGNITIONS**

- Research in the field of computer science from Lala Lajpatrai Institute Of Management.
- Full Stack Web Development Program Edureka.
- PRE-SECURITY LEARNING PATH <u>TryHackMe</u>
- M220JS: MongoDB for JavaScript Developers (Archived)
- CYBERSECURITY FUNDAMENTALS CERTIFICATE <u>TryHackMe</u>